Guide to the Women's Education Ephemera Collection, 1806-1948 RL.11876
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women's Education Ephemera collection
1806-1948
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Baskin, Lisa Unger, former owner
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
RL.11876
0.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains assorted examples of ephemeral manuscripts and printed materials collected by Lisa Unger Baskin relating to women's education, largely dating from the 19th and early 20th century. Formats include: school catalogs and prospectuses (for both New England and Parisian institutes for young women); school certificates and merit awards; tuition receipts and other financial ephemera; some images of school buildings; student workbooks, penmanship books, and other classroom exercises; examples of correspondence between female students and their family or friends; and other assorted items including a journal kept by student Sophia Jane Griffith and a student list maintained by penmanship instructor J. P. Webster.
Arrangement
Arranged by format.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Women's Education Ephemera Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from Lisa Unger Baskin in 2015.
Collection Overview
Collection contains assorted examples of ephemeral manuscripts and printed materials collected by Lisa Unger Baskin relating to women's education, largely dating from the 19th and early 20th century. Formats include: school catalogs and prospectuses (for both New England and Parisian institutes for young women); school certificates and merit awards; tuition receipts and other financial ephemera; some images of school buildings; student workbooks, penmanship books, and other classroom exercises; examples of correspondence between female students and their family or friends; and other assorted items including a journal kept by student Sophia Jane Griffith and a student list maintained by penmanship instructor J. P. Webster.
Penmanship; Copybooks; School catalogs; Young women -- Education; Students; Boarding schools -- United States; Women -- Education -- United States; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- School prospectuses and advertisements, 1850s-1910s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Assorted prospectuses and handouts advertising and describing seminaries, institutions, and schools for children (usually girls) to attend in the United States and Canada. Some prospectuses include images of the school building. Schools include: Milton (Mass.) Private School, with principal Josiah Fairbank, 1800s; Mr. Crafts School for Young Ladies (Marblehead), 1800s; Springfield English and Classical School (Springfield, Mass.), with principal Miss Laura W. Stebbins, 1800s; Rollstone Institute (Fitchburg, Mass.), with principal Miss S.B. Packard, 1859; The Elms Family and Day School for Girls (Springfield, Mass.), with Misses Porter and Champney, principals, 1868; German language and instruction (Sandnsky City), with Ph. Willner, 1851; Henniker Academy (Hanniker, N.H.), with Thomas L. Sanborn, principal, 1859; Bordentown Female College (N.J.), with Rev. Wm. C. Bowen, 1879-1880; Morgan Memorial Day Nursery (Boston, Mass.), with Miss Helen M. Paine, 1910s; Misses Lea's Seminary fees list (Fell's Point, Mass.), 1800s; Pittsfield Academy, with Henry Huse, principal, 1865-1866; Mrs. Newhall's School for Girls and Young Ladies (Boston), 1883; Hillside Manual Labor School (Amherst, N.H.), with Edward Hartshorn and H. Jane Hartshorn, 1861; Hillside Family School (Amherst, N.H.), with Edward Hartshorn and H. Jane Hartshorn, 1861; Young Ladies' Seminary (Montreal), with Mrs. C.H. Lay, principal, 1900s; Sharon Female Seminary (Darby, Penn.), with Rachel Jackson, principal, 1855; Orlead Institute for Young Ladies (Worcester, Mass.), with H.P. Dodge, principal. The Orlead prospectus includes a letter from H.W. Carstens to a friend, 1859 Apr. 3; Boylston High School for Masters and Young Ladies, Miss L. Bigelow, preceptress (with manuscript music score on reverse), 1800s; Hackettstown Institute/Centenary Collegiate Institute, New Jersey, 1880s.
- School prospectuses, Paris, 1870-1890 (Box 1)
  School prospectuses and accompanying correspondence, largely in French, regarding young women's education in Paris academies. Items include: M. U. Dupuis letter to unidentified Madame, regarding enrolling her daughter, 1879; Establishment for Young Ladies, directed by Mlle. Moppert, approximately 1880s; Les Dames Marie-Therese, Paris, approximately 1880s; Mme Wantzel's Establishment for Young Ladies, Paris, 1880s; Institution de Mesdames Martinet-Dutois, Paris, including a letter from Dutois, 1879; Mlle. Cognet Private Education, Paris, 2 copies, approximately 1880s; Miss Strickland's School testimonials, 1878; Mesdemoiselles Lacorne Establishment for Young Ladies, 2 copies, approximately 1870s; Institution de Demoiselles dirigee par Mlle Lodde, with letter from Sophie Gay to E. Lodde, 1879; Establishment for Young Ladies by Mrs. Buhon, with letter from her, 1879; Institution Anglo-Francaise de Mdm Alfred Havet, with letter from Havet to Mrs. Gair, 1879; Institution de Demoiselles Dirigee par Madame Langlet, approximately 1880s; Institution for Young Ladies, Mesdames Tribou-Labrely, Madame Dubut Successor, with letter from Dubut to Mr. William Gill, 1879; Letter from Hilda Horeeby on behalf of Institution de Desmoiselles dirigee par Mme. Aubertin, approximately 1880; Boarding-School for Young Ladies conducted by Mmes. Dadant de Perrodil et Simon, with letter, 1879; Letter from Institution de Madam Laville, 1979.
- School certificates, awards, merits, and tickets, 1810s-1910s (Box 1)
  Assorted examples and samples of student awards, passes, and other ephemera distributed by schools and relating to children's or women's education. Items include: Troy Female Seminary certificate to Abbie E. Bond, signed by principal Emma Willard, 1866 June 27; Miss Phebe Harcy, head of class, 1809 Aug. 20; Bradford Academy Female Department report card for Larissa Kimball, 1830s; Angeline W. Tottingham reward of merit for spelling, Pittsford, 1815; Mary Lucas teaching certificate, Middlesborough, 1849 June 12; Cincinnati Female Institute attendance ticket, 1840; Young Ladies Hall reward of merit to Mary P. Gramble, 1820 May 8; Miss Cranston's School reward of merit for Abby R. Manchester, 1816 Oct. 23; Attendance certificate for Merrimack County Institute for Martha H. Morse, Concord, 1852; Cheshire County Teachers' Institute, Keene, certificate for Mary Towne, 1848 Nov. 1; School Souvenir (Winterterm student list), District 18, Chesterfield Factory Village, N.H., 1869; Reward of merit for Peleg Walker, 1820s?; Reward of Merit certificate for Peleg Walker, 1820s?; Souvenir for New Rye School (includes photograph portrait of woman and student list), Epsom, N.H., 1910; Reward of merit for Lydia M. Watson, 1800s?; Rewards of merit (adhered to a board) for Mary Patrick and Sarah A. Lincoln, 1858; Wesleyan Female College library shelf location tickets (2); Miss Peck illuminated manuscript of appreciation, on vellum, Montreal, 1882; Reward of merit for Joseph Battles, by Phebe Battles, 1800s; Rewards of merit (2) for Sophronia Sturtevant, 1800s; Miss Balch's Boarding School token of appreciation, 1822 Mar. 20.
- School fundraising solicitation letters and tuition receipts, 1806-1870 (Box 1)
  Examples of printed and manuscript materials relating to school finances, including teacher payment receipt, student tuition receipts, lists, and circulars for subscribers and support for different schools. Items include: Mrs. Jarley's Wax Works, for the Benefit of the Fund for the Liberal Education of Southern Girls programme, with annotations noting the names of the performers, 1872; Blue-School for Girls list of contributors, Chester, England, 1806; Auburn Female Seminary receipt for Eliza Wright, 1843 Jan. 28; Unknown school tuition receipt for Lucretia Chapman, 1821 Oct.; British and Foreign School Society, subscribers' book for a new training school for female teachers, 1842 Aug.; Gower's Walk School solicitation for Adult Instruction for Friendless and Unprovided Orphan Daughters of Clergymen, Military, and Naval Officers, 1820 Oct.; Philadelphia School of Design for Women tuition receipt for Ms. McAllister, 1865 Sept; Pay stub for Louise Shoept(?), Ellisburgh, 1870; Account book, including tuition payments, from Pioneer Valley, 1818-1829; Academy of Dancing receipt for Susan Ward from C. Labasse, 1826; Receipt for Massachusetts Teacher subscription, 1834; Receipt for tuition to Boston Cooking School, Simmons College, for 12 practice lessons, 1903.
- School programs and events, 1836-1931 (Box 1)
  Programs and other memorabilia from assorted school activities, ceremonies, and events. Items include: N.C. State Convention of the YMCA, at Salem Academy and College, 1903 Mar. 9; New Albany Female Seminary, 1858 June 24; British Federation of University Women, London Association dinner invitation, 1931 Mar. 5; Hillsboro High School, Hillsboro Bridge, N.H. graduation exercises, 1899 June 15; A Midsummer Night's Dream, Mt. Holyoke students, 1899 June 19; Catalogue of the Officers and Students of Bradford Academy Female Department, Bradford, Mass., 1836; Dancing School invitation for Miss Harriet Brooks, Lancaster, 1844.
- School buildings, approximately 1850s-1880s (Box 1)
  Images of school buildings, including: Institution for Young Ladies on Brooklyn Heights (illustration), 1850s; Miss Burnham's Boarding School for Young Ladies, Northampton, Mass., published by A.G. Carley (photograph), 1880s.
- Student penmanship and exercises workbooks, 1810s-1879 (Box 1)
  Bound booklets and a fragment, used by students or teachers to practice penmanship or other topics. Items include: Ladies' Angular Hand blue booklet, undated; Geographical Exercises workbook for Ribston Hall (student Annie Jones), Sept. 1867; stitched booklet with penmanship and artwork by Ruth Satterly, 1800s; Penmanship and writing book, 1879; Penmanship book (student Elizabeth Louisa Christopher), 1830; Betsey Rich's Book, including penmanship and awards for spelling, Charleston, 1813; Lucy Towne copybook with sonnets and poems, Bedford, Mass., 1810s; fragment on School Penmanship by Margaret T. Lewis, 1820 June 12.
- Correspondence from students and teachers, 1811-1948 (Box 1)
  Examples of letters to and from students collected by Lisa Unger Baskin and relating to women's or girls' educational endeavors. Items include: Elizabeth H. Haight postcard of Vassar College, 1948 Aug. 26; Josslyn Flagg (Harrison, Maine) to Helen Rankin (East Denmark, Maine), 1913 Jan. 20; Maggie to Emma (Lima), regarding Milton School, 1864 Apr. 17; Mariah (Norridgwork) to friend, regarding Female Academy, 1849 Jun. 25; Lydia (Wellesley College) to Bertha, 1896 Apr. 18; Rebecah Tufts to James Cutler (her uncle, West Cambridge, Mass.), regarding Mrs. Gills Academy, 1811 May 22; Charles Gaylord(?) to C.C. Palmer, on Connecticut Literary Institution letterhead, 1865.
- Sophia Jane Griffith pass book: "Journal for the year 1850" (Box 1)
  Describes daily activities, including high school taught by Rufus C. Hardy. Believed to be based in Massachusetts.
- J. P. Webster: "Names of scholars who have been under the instruction of J. P. Webster in the art of penmanship," plus accompanying clippings, 1837-1842 (Box 1)
  Includes lists of students as well as laid-in newsprint advertisements for Webster's courses in New Hampshire; South Carolina; Hollis, Maine; and Alabama.
- Bibliography of College, Social, and University Settlements, compiled by M. Katharine Jones, College Settlements Association, 1895 (Box 1)
- New Hampshire Registry for Winter School, Union District, 1853 (Box 1)
- Student roster, grades, and student essays, from unknown place, teacher: M. G. Croswell, 1849 (Box 1)
  Croswell's list of students and their grades in various subjects, and thirteen compositions from some of the students on topics like "conversation," "health," and "time."